Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- C
  - Carroll, Martina, Feb 20, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    In this interview, Carroll discusses contact had been lost with eldest sister and when Martina came she met her for the first time (Track 2, at 7 mins she talks of meeting her sister for first time); her husband, who worked in St. Patrick’s Cathedral for 56 years; about being delighted that the Irish do not HAVE to emigrate from Ireland; and how she found leaving home very difficult.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 80 minutes long, on 1 CD. The interview took place on February 20, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Subject notes have been created by track number, and the Word file is available upon request at irisharchives@nyu.edu.
  - Carroll, Patrick, Apr 7, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 2 hours and 45 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place on April 7, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Patrick Carroll (b. New York, New York, 1965) is 2nd generation Irish through his mother, Martina Carroll, and 3rd generation Irish through his father. He was raised in Manhattan's Stuyvesant Town. He is a Special Agent for the US Department of Justice, Federal Bureau of Investigation.
  - Casey, Sr. Noreen, Apr 16, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 90 minutes long, on 1 CD. The interview took place on April 16, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Sr. Noreen Casey (b. Knocknagree, County Cork, Ireland, 1920) is a Missionary Franciscan Sister, who spent her career in education and retired as a school principal in Savannah, Georgia.
  - Cassidy, Daniel, Jun 20, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Daniel Cassidy (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1943, d. San Francisco, California, 2008) was a musician, author, labor activist, and teacher. He was the founder and co-director of the Irish Studies Program at the New College of California in San Francisco, CA. His book How the Irish Invented Slang: The Secret Language of the Crossroads won the American Book Award in 2007.
    In this oral history Cassidy, author and scholar, traces the link between his family history his involvement in Irish Studies, and the origins of his research which culminated in How the Irish Invented Slang. In a largely chronological manner, Cassidy starts by discussing his Brooklyn roots; his parents; his education; Vietnam; his battle with drugs and twenty-three month stay at Phoenix House; friendships with comedian George Carlin and musician Kenny Rankin; and the meaning of Irish identity. After starting off with a clear New York/East Coast focus, the narrative then shifts geographically to Cassidy’s life in California and most particularly in San Francisco. Topics like his writing (his screenplay, The Volunteer, was sold to Francis Ford Coppola), labor organizing, and his move into teaching are covered. Cassidy engages in a detailed discussion of language and slang, in the context of Irish American culture, with his long-time friend Peter Quinn, author of Banished Children of Eve. Cassidy provides an insider’s perspective on the day JFK was assassinated as a rookie journalist in the newsroom of the New York Times. The interview concludes with Cassidy emphasizing the extent to which Irish American scholarship awaits thorough excavation, by contending that immense research potential sits like ‘gold nuggets’ on the ground.
    Danny Cassidy was interviewed in his home in San Francisco on July 20, 2008 by Peter Quinn. This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. It is 148 minutes and 49 seconds long, on three CDs, and has been logged at five minute intervals.
    This interview has been logged at five-minute intervals, and the Word file is available upon request at irisharchives@nyu.edu.
  - Clancy, Cummin, Apr 29, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Cummin Clancy (b. Oughterard, County Galway, Ireland, 1922) is an insurance broker with the firm of Clancy and Clancy Brokerage Ltd. in Garden City, New York. A former Olympic athlete (1948 Games in London), he is the founder of the Long Island Chapter of the Friendly Sons of St. Patrick.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 80 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on April 29, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Clancy, Liam, Mar 29, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Liam Clancy (b. Carrick-On-Suir, County Tipperary, Ireland, 1935, d. Cork, County Cork, Ireland, 2009), musician, vocalist, and youngest member of the Clancy Brothers and Tommy Makem, a folk supergroup which revolutionized Irish traditional music in the United States. He published his memoir The Mountain of the Women in 2001.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 90 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on March 29, 2009, at the Washington Square Hotel, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Cody, Rena, Jul 26, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Rena Cody (b. Templemore, Co. Tipperary, Ireland, 1952), co-founder of the Irish Immigration Center in Boston, she worked at Neponset Health Center. She returned to Ireland in 1993 and works as a local government Social Exclusion Officer.
  - Collins, John, Apr 5, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    John P. Collins (b. Manhattan, New York, 1939), the son of immigrants from Co. Limerick, has been a judge for the New York City Criminal Court since 1978. He received his B.S. from Fordham University and his J.D. from New York University. In the 1960s he was active in the movement to counter restrictions on emigration from Ireland.
  - Conlon, Ray, Aug 24, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Connolly, Marie, Jun 23, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Marie Connolly (b. New York, 1935), raised in County Longford, Ireland, from the age of two, she returned to Astoria, NY as a teenager in 1949. She later worked in admissions for the Berkeley School and the Wood School in Manhattan before raising three children on Long Island.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 100 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in Wantagh, NY, on February 26, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Conway, Kevin, May 25, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Kevin Conway (b. Manchester, England, 1966) grew up near Manchester, UK, where his parents had emigrated in the 1950s. The family returned to Finny, Co. Galway in 1981. He came to the United States in 1988, and again in 1990, married an American wife in 1991, and heads the imaging Research Laboratory at Massachussetts General Hospital.
  - Cook, Terri Connolly, Oct 30, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Subject headings have been created by track number, and the Excel file is available upon request at irisharchives@nyu.edu.
    The interview with Terri Connolly Cook touches on several themes, including: being an Irish Catholic woman in corporate America; 9/11 and Irish terrorism; claddagh rings found after 9/11; Irish America and being Democrat-(‘we were all raised to be democrats’) and the move to Republican party; Obama and the younger generation; and JFK.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview is approximately 110 minutes long. The interview took place in New York on October 20, 2008, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Terri Connolly Cook (b. New York, New York, 1942), retired fashion industry executive, grew up in the Mott Haven and Bedford Park sections of the Bronx, New York. The daughter of 1920s immigrants, she curated the 2008 photo exhibition “The Monaghan Society in New York” at the Monaghan County Museum in Ireland.
  - Cooke, Caitriona, May 25, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Caitriona Cooke (b. Dublin, Ireland, 1951) was a schoolteacher in Ireland who re-trained as a conservation consultant in Boston, specializing in energy efficiency systems for buildings.
  - Corcoran, Sr. Eileen, Jul 14, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Eileen Corcoran of the Sisters of St. Dominic (b. Bronx, New York, 1941), the daughter of Irish immigrants from Counties Donegal and Cork, was raised in the Parkchester section of the Bronx. Through her vocation with the Dominican sisters, she has worked on creating art retreats, fundraising, and teaching religious and physical education, most recently at Our Lady Queen of Martyrs in Centerport, New York.
  - Costello, Frank, Apr 9, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Frank Costello (b. Newark, New Jersey, 1955) is Director of Costello Associates in Belfast, a firm that promotes community development investment in Ireland and the U.S. Born in Newark, NJ, he attended boarding school at St. Mary’s College, Galway, while a teenager, later earning a Ph.D. from Boston College in 1992. He is the author of The Irish Revolution and its Aftermath 1916–1923: Years of Revolt (2002).
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 3 hours long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in Newark, NJ, on April 9, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Cronacher, Lola Lee, Feb 15, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Lola Lee Cronacher (b. Floral Park, New York, 1934) is a retired school teacher. Raised in Hollis, Queens, her mother was from Tralee, Co. Kerry and her father was an Irish American from Brooklyn.
  - Crotty, Paul, Mar 10, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Some of the topics this interview covers include: Buffalo Irish; Crotty's grandparents, who were immigrants from Clare, his dad, a lawyer, and he is a judge; Irishness, Catholicism, Democrats; worldview of Irish Catholics when he was coming up; how all Irish Catholic communities had a similar make-up (which he noticed when he went to Notre Dame); and Ireland and poverty.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 120 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on March 10, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Paul Crotty (b. Buffalo, New York, 1941), US District Court Justice for the Southern District of New York, was raised in Buffalo, New York. He is the grandson of immigrants from Co. Clare and a former partner in the law firm of Donovan, Leisure, Newton & Irvine.
  - Culhane, Noreen M., Dec 7, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    The interview is approximately 1 hour, 4 minutes, and 40 seconds long. The interview took place on December 7, 2006, and the interviewers were Lorraine Saxton and Marion R. Casey.
    Noreen M. Culhane (b. Bronx, New York, 1950) is an Executive Vice President at the New York Stock Exchange and the 1970 New York Rose of Tralee.
  - Cullen, Fr. Daniel, May 6, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Father Daniel Cullen (b. Larne, County Antrim, Ireland, 1920) served in the Society of African Missions (SMA) for more than sixty years. He worked in Liberia and then, for nineteen years, as a fundraiser for the SMA in the United States.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is on 2 CDs. The interview took place in Tenafly, NJ, on May 6, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Cullen, James, Dec 9, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    James Cullen (b. Astoria, New York, 1945) was born in New York but stayed with relatives in Co. Offaly for some time as a child. The son of Irish immigrants from Cos. Offaly and Roscommon, he has had a long career in law and was elected as the first President of the Brehon Law Society n 1978. He is a retired brigadier general in the United States Army Reserve Judge Advocate General's Corps, and was involved in the movement to ban the use of torture by the United States after the Abu Ghraib abuses were brought to light.
  - Cullen, Kevin, Oct 18, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Kevin Cullen (b. Malden, MA, 1958) is a Pulitzer Prize- winning Boston Globe journalist who has reported on immigration, Northern Ireland, and the Whitey Bulger case. He also contributes to Irish radio NewsTalkFM.
  - Cullimore, John, Jul 27, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    John Cullimore (b. Wexford Town, Co. Wexford, Ireland, 1959) established a successful painting/renovation company specializing in the rehabilitation of Victorian homes in Cambridge, MA; returned to Ireland in 1996.
  - Cunningham, Joseph, Mar 28, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Joseph Cunningham (b. Crusheen, Co. Clare, Ireland, 1912) emigrated to New York in 1929 and played accordion for sixty years with the Joe Cunningham Band. He raised five children in Yonkers.
  - Curran, Sean, Mar 28, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 150 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place in New York on March 18, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Sean Curran (b. Boston, Massachusetts, 1961) a modern dancer and choreographer, is the son of immigrants from Counties Cork and Roscommon. A former Irish step dancer, lead dancer with the Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company, and cast member of Stomp!, he founded the Sean Curran Company in New York in 1997.
- D
  - Daly, Anita, Jun 28, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Anita Daly (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1953) is the founder and president of Daly Communications, a music marketing company that includes a roster of Irish musicians such as Van Morrison, Clannad, and Eileen Ivers.
  - D'Arcy, Kathleen Walsh (two interviews), Feb 12, 2009-Apr 22, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Kathleen Kearney Walsh Papers (AIA 029)
    Kathleen Walsh D’Arcy (b. 1948), a social worker, writer, and organizer of the St. Pat’s for All Parade in Queens (est. 2005), is the daughter of 1920s immigrants from Co. Offaly and Co. Tipperary. She co-edited two fiction collections by Irish women writers, Territories of the Voice (1990) and A Green and Mortal Sound (2001).
    Some of the themes that D'Arcy focuses on in these interviews include: class divisions in Irish post-war community and how Kathleen related in an up-scale school environment; growing up in an extremely Irish-oriented household; parents were very open and Kathleen thinks that they were unique in that way (track 4); she was in a convent, as a novitiate, for a year; McNiff school of dancing (track 5); and her work in Dublin in the early 1970s.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview took place over two sessions: February 12, 2009 and April 22, 2009. The 2/12/09 interview is approximately 2 hours long and on two CDs, and the 4/22/09 interview is approximately 70 minutes long. The interviews both took place in New York, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Davis, Ashley, Apr 8, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Ashley Davis (b. Kansas City, Kansas, 1976) is a singer of both her own original music and of traditional songs in the Celtic languages. She received her MA from the University of Limerick in Traditional Irish Music. In 2006 she traveled to the Isle of Man to capture and record the native Manx language as well as the stories and music of the island. She released a CD Songs of the Celtic Winter in 2012.
  - Deegan, Seamus, Feb 25, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Seamus Deegan (b. Dunlavin, Co. Wicklow, 1942), a social worker, emigrated in 1966, to serve as a priest for the Diocese of Rockville Centre in Mineola, New York. In 1974 he decided to leave the priesthood and pursued graduate studies in psychology and social work.
  - Delaney, Agnes, Jul 12, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Agnes Delaney (b. Ardnagall, Co. Galway, 1943) emigrated to the United States in 1964. After completing a Masters degree in Social Work and Health Care Administration at Columbia University, she worked for more than two decades in the field of healthcare in the New York area. Since 2005, she has been Chairperson of the Board of Directors, Aisling Irish Community Center in Yonkers.
  - Dennehy, Thomas, Mar 19, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 80 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on March 19, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Thomas Dennehy (b. Cork, Co. Cork, 1938), a bus driver, emigrated with his family to New Jersey in 1982 after a period living in England and Ireland.
  - Dolan, Brendan, Nov 12, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Brendan Dolan (b. Manhattan, New York, 1966), a member of the Andy Statman Quartet and the Pride of New York, is a classically trained pianist and Irish traditional musician who has written music for television and film. The son of Felix and Joan Dolan, he holds an MA in Irish and Irish American Studies from New York University.
  - Dolan, Felix, Feb 25, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Felix Dolan (b. Bronx, New York, 1937), a renowned Irish traditional music pianist who was raised in the Highbridge section of the Bronx, is the son of immigrants from Counties Leitrim and Mayo. In 1958 he was a founding member of the New York Ceili Band. From 1963-1996 he worked for IBM as a computer programmer and in computer information security, retiring as a Director of Information at IBM. In 1997 he was inducted into the Comhaltas Ceoltóirí Éireann, Mid-Atlantic Region, Hall of Fame.
  - Dolan, Joan, Nov 16, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Joan Dolan’s first memories come from her time as a child growing up in Ireland. Her mother had moved her there from New York when she was only two and a half years old to live with her grandparents and her uncle. She had grown up on a small farm in Killarue, and she attended National School in Cavan until the age of eleven. Her parents and had come back to Ireland in order to bring her back to the United States. She has thought about her return to America at age eleven after spending nine years in Ireland. Joan only knew life on the small farm on which she lived. She felt that moving to New York was both exciting; however she has second guessed her parents’ decision to bring her back to the United States. She does not have regrets about returned when she did, as affirms that she has a wonderful life here. She does; however, remember that her uncle wished that she could have stayed until she were grown up, as she brought happiness to the lives of two older people and a bachelor. She thinks perhaps she should have left as a seventeen or eighteen year old. Joan admits that is was difficult reunite with her parents since she really did not know them. She began to know her parents only after she was brought back from Ireland when she was eleven years old in April of 1948. She describes her father as a quiet man who was dedicated to his family and his work. Her mother was a talented cook who had received on the job training in her first years as an immigrant in Providence, Rhode Island.
    Although she is happy with the way events of her life have turned out, Joan wonders what her life would have been like if she had stayed in Ireland. She does feel; however, that she would have had to have left Ireland in order to immigrate to the United States anyway. It just would have been a matter of time as there would have been little room for her on the farm, and there were few jobs to be found in Ireland. Since she did return at a young age; however, she had to adjust to American life. She recalls the drastic change, “From Killarue to Times Square, my goodness.” She attended St. Jean Baptiste High School on the Upper East Side where she admits that it was difficult to fit in at first. The immigrant mentality focused on assimilation. Joan remembers that she did not want to project an image of Irishness in school; rather, she wished to be seen as an American. These feelings changed as she grew past her adolescence, and she wished to explore and promote her Irish culture.
    When Joan was twelve years old, her parents enrolled her in Irish dancing classes in 1949 under the direction James McKenna. She describes him as a strict, yet effective instructor. She had lost interest in dancing after a year of lessons, and she decided to quit. When she was nineteen, Joan resumed Irish dancing under the direction of Peter and Cyril McNiff. She became one of their ceili dancers, and she danced competitively for four years. She describes her time she spent dancing as one of the greatest parts of her life—she danced because she enjoyed dancing, and so she could be around the friends she made in her ceili, including Andy McCann, Eva McManus, Peter McNiff, Cyril McNiff, Hannah O’Leary, Larry Reddigan, Peter Smith, Gerry Wallace, Lori Walsh, Mike Bergin Peggy Bergin, Edmund Brown, Joan Cass, Eugene Clancy, Pat Clancy, and Jimmy Erwin. She described the ceili uniforms of her team as being quite simple—green skirts, white stockings, white shirt, and a black dance jacket. She compares those more traditional outfits to many of the new styles used in Irish dancing today. She very much approves of popular productions such as Riverdance because have brought Irish dancing into the mainstream; however, the outfits—wigs, outrageous colors, and fancy embroidery—really do not embody the spirit of the dance; rather they commercialize the Irish dancing.
    After Joan married Felix Dolan, she lived in the Woodlawn and Highbridge sections of the Bronx. Both areas were decidedly Irish; however once she had kids, the Dolan family moved to Golden’s Bridge in Westchester County, NY. She believes that she has gravitated towards people with common interests. Even though this section of Westchester was ethnically diverse, Joan managed to find many Irish friends, including her best friend Ann McEnearny.
    Joan sincerely believes that it is important that her Irish culture lives on through the generations. Joan gave her children traditional Irish names, and she afforded all of them Irish dancing lessons. Her children have now named their own children traditional Irish names, and some of them have begun Irish dance lessons. In addition to dance, Joan also believed that attending Irish events as a family promoted the preservation of Irish culture. Joan has practiced what she believes as the Dolan family has marched annually with the Gaelic League in the St. Patrick’s Day Parade. Today Joan continues to attend ceilis as she still retains her passion for dancing.
    This oral history with Joan Dolan was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR 420. It is 120 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on November 16, 2006, and the interviewers were Andrew Ciancimino and Marion R. Casey.
    Joan Dolan (b. New York, New York, 1937), former McNiff dancer, founding member of the Bedford (NY) Ceili group, and wife of Irish traditional pianist Felix Dolan.
  - Donnelly, John, Oct 25, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview is approximately 130 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place In New York on October 26, 2008, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Doran, Mary, Aug 7, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Mary Doran (b. Dublin, Ireland, 1952) worked as an architect, established the Irish Film Association in New York City, and returned to Ireland in 1997.
  - Dorgan, Mike, Apr 24, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Mike Dorgan (b. Whitechurch, Co. Cork, 1936) is the past president of the Cork Association of New York.
  - Drew, Fr. James, Feb 24, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Fr. James Drew (b. Croagh Hill, Co. Cork, Ireland, 1948) came to the United States in 1971. He was ordained in the Diocese of Honolulu in 1974 and serves as the administrator for Our Lady of the Snow parish in Blue Point, New York.
  - Driscoll, John, Apr 21, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Duggan, Donal, Jul 31, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 33)